<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blog on Rui Vieira</title><link>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/</link><description>Recent content in Blog on Rui Vieira</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-uk</language><atom:link href="https://ruivieira.dev/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Plan 9 design</title><link>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/2024-01-28.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/2024-01-28.html</guid><description>Plan 9&amp;rsquo;s designAn interesting quote from Ron Minnich about Plan 9&amp;rsquo;s design:
On Plan 9, the rule tends to be: if feature(X) can&amp;rsquo;t be implemented in a way that works for everything, don&amp;rsquo;t do it. No special cases allowed;</description></item><item><title>BSD mascot</title><link>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/2024-01-21.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/2024-01-21.html</guid><description>There is an interesting post by Jacob Elder where I learned that John Lassetter (of Toy Story, A Bug&amp;rsquo;s Life, Cars and Cars 2) also created the BSD mascot.
Read more about UNIX in general or BSD in particular.</description></item><item><title>KServe logging</title><link>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/2023-09-27.html</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/2023-09-27.html</guid><description>In Kubernetes, labels serve as a mechanism to organize and select groupings of objects. They are key-value pairs associated with objects and can be used to apply operations on a subset of objects. Kustomize is a tool that allows us to manage these configurations efficiently.
Let’s consider a project named foo. The project has various Kubernetes objects labeled with app: foo. Now, suppose there is a requirement to change the label to app: bar.</description></item><item><title>Orca's fashion</title><link>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/2023-09-18.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/2023-09-18.html</guid><description>The waters around the Iberian Peninsula (mostly reported off the Spanish and Portuguese coasts) have been of interest for marine biologists due to a notable increase in interactions between orcas and boats. Having intricate social structures and intelligence, orcas display behaviours that may be influenced by a multitude of factors such as environmental and social ones.
Scientists postulate that these interactions might be representative of a transient &amp;ldquo;fad&amp;rdquo; within orca pods.</description></item><item><title>Modernism and Gazette</title><link>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/2023-09-16.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/2023-09-16.html</guid><description>Recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading a fair bit about John Dos Passos, and while I haven&amp;rsquo;t still read any of his books, his approach to literature seems quite avant-garde for his time. The &amp;ldquo;USA Trilogy&amp;rdquo; is frequently cited as a significant exploration of American life in the early 20th century, using techniques like the &amp;ldquo;Newsreel&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;Camera Eye&amp;rdquo; to tell his narratives. From the discussions and summaries I&amp;rsquo;ve encountered, Dos Passos seemed to have a knack for interweaving fiction with the pressing sociopolitical issues of his era.</description></item><item><title>KNative missing CRDs</title><link>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/2023-09-07.html</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/2023-09-07.html</guid><description>If you&amp;rsquo;re using Kubernetes 1.27.3 to install KServe 0.9 or 0.10, you might encounter this error:
resource mapping not found for name: &amp;#34;activator&amp;#34; namespace: &amp;#34;knative-serving&amp;#34; from &amp;#34;https://github.com/knative/serving/releases/download/knative-v1.7.0/serving-core.yaml&amp;#34;: no matches for kind &amp;#34;HorizontalPodAutoscaler&amp;#34; in version &amp;#34;autoscaling/v2beta2&amp;#34; ensure CRDs are installed first resource mapping not found for name: &amp;#34;webhook&amp;#34; namespace: &amp;#34;knative-serving&amp;#34; from &amp;#34;https://github.com/knative/serving/releases/download/knative-v1.7.0/serving-core.yaml&amp;#34;: no matches for kind &amp;#34;HorizontalPodAutoscaler&amp;#34; in version &amp;#34;autoscaling/v2beta2&amp;#34; Here&amp;rsquo;s the main issue:
Kubernetes 1.27.3 no longer supports the autoscaling/v2beta2 API version of HorizontalPodAutoscaler.</description></item><item><title>JUnit null and empty sources</title><link>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/2023-09-05.html</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/2023-09-05.html</guid><description>Today I learned about JUnit&amp;rsquo;s ability to use null sources in conjunction with @ParamterizedTest. Example:
@ParameterizedTest @NullAndEmptySource @ValueSource(strings = {&amp;#34;test&amp;#34;, &amp;#34;JUnit&amp;#34;}) void nullAndEmptyTest(String text) { Assertions.assertTrue(text == null || text.trim().isEmpty() || &amp;#34;test&amp;#34;.equals(text) || &amp;#34;JUnit&amp;#34;.equals(text)); } There&amp;rsquo;s also @NullSource and @EmptySource.</description></item><item><title>LunarVim</title><link>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/2023-09-04.html</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/2023-09-04.html</guid><description>Been trying out NeoVim in the format of LunarVim.
To use with a GUI on macOS, I use NeoVide, with the command
neovide --neovim-bin ~/.local/bin/lvim --multigrid --maximized --frame none If you are planning on using Neovim I recommend using a tree-sitter-aware theme. You can find a list here. My personal favourites are modus and gruvbox-material.</description></item><item><title>Hatch Poetry</title><link>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/2023-09-03.html</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/2023-09-03.html</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been a long-time user of Poetry for my Python projects, and it&amp;rsquo;s been a welcome change. However, my recent exploration into Hatch has sparked my interest.
Poetry simplifies dependency management with its unified pyproject.toml, but Hatch excels in scenarios requiring complex workflows. A common personal use-case is Docker multi-stage builds. Hatch, with its conventional requirements.txt and setup.py, offers more granular control, making complex configurations easier.
Hatch also aligns closely with the existing Python ecosystem due to its use of traditional setup files, linking old with new workflows, ensuring a better integration.</description></item><item><title>Exception Bubbling in Python</title><link>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/2023-09-02.html</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ruivieira.dev/blog/2023-09-02.html</guid><description>One aspect of Java that occasionally nudges at me is its explicit approach to exception handling. Java requires developers to either handle exceptions via try-catch blocks or declare them in method signatures. While it does enforce robustness, it sometimes feels a bit too constrained, especially when compared to the flexible nature of Python.
Recently, I crafted a solution in Python for k8sutils. Instead of the usual explicit exception handling or modifying method signatures, I created a Python decorator - akin to annotations in Java - that substitutes an exception for another without altering the underlying code.</description></item></channel></rss>